Finding Aid for the Verne Austin Papers, 1943-1945 LSC.2010.04
UCLA Library Special Collections
- The Japanese Situation at Tule Lake, 1.0 linear ft.
  - Documentary exhibits (Box 43, Box 44)
    - A copy of the WRA Internal Security Follow Up Case Report on Reverand Thomas Grubbs, minister of the Tule Lake Union Church., July 19, 1944; (2pp.) (Box 44, Folder 3)
    - A report by Battalion Intelligence Officer., July 25, 1944.; (1p.) (Box 44, Folder 3)
      re Goon squad activities in the Colony.
    - Translated copies of Japanese notices posted in men's washrooms in the Colony, which reported a hunger strike started by stockade internees on July 19, 1944 and asked for Colonists' support., July 27, 1944; (2pp.) (Box 44, Folder 3)
    - Copy of the new WRA regulations for the stockade., July 28, 1944; (1p.) (Box 44, Folder 3)
    - Record of Events., August 1944; (6pp.) (Box 44, Folder 4)
    - A report by the Office of Battalion Intelligence Officer., August 3, 1944; (2pp.) (Box 44, Folder 4)
      re Kaoru Harry Fujimoto, resident in Livingston, Montana, who came to Tule Lake without a travel permit to visit his family.
    - Documents., ca. December 1943-August 4, 1944; (5 items) (Box 44, Folder 4)
      re the claim of Mary Shin, a Nisei internee in the Tule Lake Center, for a necklace and $55.00 cash which disappeared from the bags confiscated by the Army during the November 26, 1943 search operation.
    - A copy of a new WRA regulation on the admission of visitors to the center (Special Order no. 4)., August 9, 1944; (2pp.) (Box 44, Folder 4)
    - Memorandum issued by Best to WRA personnel and interness., August 9, 1944; (1p.) (Box 44, Folder 4)
      re Installation of a turnstile gate on the site of old gate no. 3.
    - A confidential report of the Monitoring Officer of the Federal Communications Commission to Austin., August 10, 1944; (1p.) (Box 44, Folder 4)
      re Radio monitoring in vicinity of the Tule Lake Center.
    - A report of Battalion Intelligence Officer, August 12, 1944; (2pp.) (Box 44, Folder 4)
      re Disturbance caused by wives of the stockade internees at the WRA internal security on August 11, 1944.
    - A report by Battalion Intelligence Officer., August 12, 1944; (2 items) (Box 44, Folder 4)
      re A report submitted by Sergeant Kelly on the disturbance at Gate no. 3 caused by three Japanese women. Includes a photograph.
    - A report by Battalion Intelligence Officer., August 17, 1944; (2pp.) (Box 44, Folder 4)
      re Rumors circulated in the Colony.
    - The Newell Star, vol. I, no. 25., August 17, 1944; (6pp.) (Box 44, Folder 4)
    - Tsuru Reiko Shimp, no. 26., August 17, 1944; ( 4pp.) (Box 44, Folder 4)
    - The Newell Star, vol. I, no. 26., August 24, 1944; (6pp.) (Box 44, Folder 4)
    - Tsuru Reiko Shimp, no. 27., August 24, 1944; (4pp.) (Box 44, Folder 4)
    - A report by Battalion Intelligence Officer., August 26, 1944; (2pp.) (Box 44, Folder 4)
      re An informer's report on activities of Willard Schmidt, Chief of Internal Security, WRA.
    - Letter, Best to Austin., August 26, 1944; (2pp.) (Box 44, Folder 4)
      re Direct contacts between some internees and the Army, and the administrative responsibilities of the WWA.
    - The Newell Star, vol. I, no. 27., August 31, 1944; (6pp.) (Box 44, Folder 4)
    - Tsuru Reiko Shimp, no. 28., August 31, 1944; (4pp.) (Box 44, Folder 4)
    - Record of Events., September 1944 (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - A report by Battalion Intelligence Officer., September 4, 1944; (1p.) (Box 44, Folder 5)
      re An attempt of Schmidt, WRA Chief Internal Security Officer, to establish a rapport.
    - Memorandum, Battalion Intelligence Officer to Austin., September 5, 1944; (1p.) (Box 44, Folder 5)
      re Return of Hashimoto Noboru and Makihara Wataru, stockade internees, to the Colony.
    - Memorandum, Sergeant Yeramian to Captain Forbes, Battalion Intelligence Officer., September 9, 1944; (1p.) (Box 44, Folder 5)
      re Issuance of a travel permit to Reverand Kai Shizuo, alleged chief instigator of the November disturbance, to Alturas for questioning by the U.S. District Attorney.
    - Memorandum, WRA Administrative Police Department to Austin., September 20, 1944; (1p.) (Box 44, Folder 5)
      re Issuance of a badge to a new member of the department.
    - Memorandum, H.L. Black, Acting Project Director, to Austin., September 11, 1944; (1p.) (Box 44, Folder 5)
      re Resignation of Schmidt, and appointment of J.B. Cook as Acting Chief of the WRA Internal Security.
    - A typewritten copy of a recent Washington Post article, which was reprinted in the September 23, 1944 issue of the Manzanar Free Press., (1p.) (Box 44, Folder 5)
      The article criticized the role of the Army in the West Coast evacuation of the Japanese.
    - A copy of an information leaflet, What is a RESEGREGATION and What does it MEAN., ca. September 25, 1944; (2pp.) (Box 44, Folder 5)
      distributed among the internees.
    - A report by Battalion Intelligence Officer., September 28, 1944; (1p.) (Box 44, Folder 5)
      re Rumors about Reverand Kai Shizuo.
    - The Newell Star, vol. I, no. 31., September 28, 1944; (6pp.) (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - Tsuru Reiko Shimp, no. 32., September 28, 1944; (4pp.) (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - A report by Sergeant Yeramian., September 29, 1944; (4pp.) (Box 44, Folder 5)
      re Information obtained from Rosalie Hankey (rumors from the Colony).
    - Record of Events., October 1944; (4pp.) (Box 44, Folder 6)
    - Our gratitude and wishes to the residents of the Tule Lake Center, signed by Kai Shizuo and 13 other former stockade internees., October 3, 1944; (Mimeographed leaflet. 1p.) (Box 44, Folder 6)
      Circulated in the Center starting October 3, 1944. Its distribution was stopped by WRA on the next day.
    - The Newell Star, vol. I, no. 32., October 5, 1944; (4pp.) (Box 44, Folder 6)
    - Tsuru Reiko Shimp, no. 33., October 5, 1944; (4pp.) (Box 44, Folder 6)
    - The Newell Star, vol. I, no. 35., October 26, 1944; (4pp.) (Box 44, Folder 6)
    - Tsuru Reiko Shimp, no. 36., October 26, 1944; (4pp.) (Box 44, Folder 6)
    - A copy of a letter, Katharine Taft to Robert Sibley., October 30, 1944; (4pp.) (Box 44, Folder 6)
      re Tule Lake Center.
    - A confidential memorandum issued by Intelligence Division, Ninth Service Command., October 31, 1944; (1p.) (Box 44, Folder 6)
      re Occurrence of a disturbance at Tule Lake on November 3, 1944.
    - Record of Events., November 1944; (2pp.) (Box 44, Folder 7)
    - The Newell Star, vol. I, no. 36., November 2, 1944; (6pp.) (Box 44, Folder 7)
    - Tsuru Reiko Shimp, no. 37., November 2, 1944; (4pp.) (Box 44, Folder 7)
    - Memoranda, Battalion Intelligence Officer to Austin., November 20, 1944; (2pp.) (Box 44, Folder 7)
      re Japanese language publications at Tule Lake, Dot [characters] [Angry Waves] and Tessaku [characters] [Iron Fence], obtained by the Office of Intelligence Officer.
    - A report by Battalion Intelligence Officer., November 29, 1944; (2pp.) (Box 44, Folder 7)
      re Rumors about the former stockade internees.
    - Record of Events., December 1944; (3pp.) (Box 44, Folder 8)
    - Memorandum, Battalion Intelligence Officer to Austin., December 9, 1944; (1p.) (Box 44, Folder 8)
      re Discovery of a buried wooden box containing the bodies of 3 prematurely born Japanese babies.
    - A report by Sergeant Yeramian., December 9, 1944; (1p.) (Box 44, Folder 8)
      re Rumors from the Colony.
    - Memorandum, Battalion Intelligence Officer to Austin., December 11, 1944; (1p.) (Box 44, Folder 8)
      re Japanese mail censoring at Tule Lake City Post Office.
    - The Newell Star, vol. I, no. 42., December 14, 1944; (3pp.) (Box 44, Folder 8)
    - Tsuru Reiko Shimp, no. 34., December 14, 1944; (2pp.) (Box 44, Folder 8)
    - Memorandum, Battalion Intelligence Officer to Austin., December 16, 1944; (2pp.) (Box 44, Folder 8)
      re Disturbance in the Colony on December 15, 1944.
    - The Newell Star, extra issue., December 19, 1944; (6pp.) (Box 44, Folder 8)
    - Tsuru Reiko Shimp, extra issue., December 19, 1944; (4pp.) (Box 44, Folder 8)
    - A report by the Office of Battalion Intelligence Officer., December 19, 1944; (1p.) (Box 44, Folder 8)
      re Information obtained from Dr. Marks on the buried bodies of 3 prematurely born babies.
    - A report by Battalion Intelligence Officer., December 22, 1944; (5pp.) (Box 44, Folder 8)
      re Trial of the 11 internees accused of causing a disturbance in the Colony on December 15, 1944.
    - A report by Battalion Intelligence Officer., December 23, 1944; (1p.) (Box 44, Folder 8)
      re Translated Table of Contents of the Dot, [no. 4], November 1944.
    - Record of Events., January 1945; (3pp.) (Box 44, Folder 9)
    - The Newell Star, vol. II, no. 1., January 1, 1945; (16pp.) (Box 44, Folder 9)
    - A copy of the final decision of Martin P. Gunderson, Acting Project Director who judged those internees involved in the December 15, 1944 disturbance at Tule Lake., January 3, 1945; (2pp.) (Box 44, Folder 9)
    - The Newell Star, vol. II, no. 2., January 11, 1945; (6pp.) (Box 44, Folder 9)
    - Tsuru Reiko Shimp, no. 46., January 11, 1945; (3pp.) (Box 44, Folder 9)
    - The Newell Star, vol. II, no. 4., January 25, 1945; (5pp.) (Box 44, Folder 9)
    - Tsuru Reiko Shimp, no. 48., January 25, 1945; (4pp.) (Box 44, Folder 9)
    - Copies of the WRA reports and related documents on subversive political groups in the Tule Lake Center, forwarded by the WRA Internal Security Officer to Austin., January 8, 1945 (Box 44, Folder 9)
      1. A copy of the WRA Internal Security confidential report, August 15, 1944. re Sokoku Kenkyu Seinen Kai [characters] [Greater Asia Youth Study Group], an organization formed by those internees who desired the repatriation and expatriation in August 1944. Includes short biographical sketches of 8 principal members of the group. 12pp.
      2. A copy of the Records of the Sokoku Kenkyu Seinenkai, n.d. (ca. August 1944). Includes translated copies of the purpose of establishment, regulations, rosters of the members of the Board of Directors and other officers, and Inauguration Ceremony Program. 7pp.
      3. A copy of a WRA Administrative Police report, August 24, 1944. re The aim and purpose of the Sokoku Kenkyu Seinenkai. 2pp.
      4. A copy of a WRA Administrative Police report, November 1, 1944. re The Sokoku Kenkyu Seinendan (Seinenkai) and the resegregation movement in the Tule Lake Center. 3pp.
      5. A copy of a WRA Administrative Police report, December 2, 1944. re The resegregation movement and the formation of the Sokoku Kenkyu Seinendan. 3pp.
      6. English translation of a letter intercepted by the WRA Internal Security. From an internee who left for Santa Fe for expatriation to another remaining in the Tule Lake Center. December 27, 1944. 1p.
      7. A copy of a WRA Administrative Police report, January 3, 1945. re A supplementary report on subversive political activities in the Tule Lake Colony. 2pp.
      8. A copy of a WRA Administrative Police report, January 4, 1945. re A supplementary report on subversive activities of political groups in the Colony. 1p.
      9. A copy of a WRA Administrative Police report, n.d. re An English translation of the general meaning of an announcement written in Japanese and distributed in the Colony by the Sokuji Kikoku Hshidan [characters] and Hokoku Seinendan [characters], dated December 27, 1944. 2pp.
      10. A copy of the WRA Administrative Police report, January 17, 1945. re Names of the officers in ward-based organizations of the Sokuji Kikoku Hshidan as of January 10, 1944. 6pp.
      11. A copy of a letter, John L. Burling, U.S. Attorney, Department of Justice, to Chairmen of the Sokuji kikoku hshi dan and Hokoku Seinendan, January 18, 1945. re Political activities in the internment camp. (The letter was a reply to the letter and telegram forwarded to the Attorney General on January 1 & 6, 1945, respectively.). 5pp.
      12. A photograph of approximately 2,000 members of the Seinendan organizations bedding the internees who were going to Santa Fe farewell, January 26, 1945. (1 item).
      13. Memorandum, Best to Austin, January 26, 1945. re Order prohibiting those internees who wear an external garment bearing a Japanese emblem or insignia from leaving the colony proper. 1p.
      14. WRA Information Bulletin no. 3, January 29, 1945. re Dillon S. Myer's statement to the residents of Tule Lake Center. 1p.
    - Record of Events., February 1945; (3pp.) (Box 44, Folder 10)
    - The Newell Star, vol. II, no. 5., February 1, 1945; (5pp.) (Box 44, Folder 10)
    - Tsuru Reiko Shimp, no.49., February 1, 1945; (4pp.) (Box 44, Folder 10)
    - A copy of a teletype message, Charles M. Rothstein, Hearing Officer of the Department of Justice, to Herbert Wechsler, Assistant Attorney General., February 7, 1945; (7pp.) (Box 44, Folder 10)
      re Apprehension of 635 Nisei officers of the Seinendan organizations who renounced their United States citizenship, and 15 Issei officers and leaders of subversive organizations as alien enemies.
    - The Newell Star, vol. II, no. 6., February 9, 1945; (5pp.) (Box 44, Folder 10)
    - Tsuru Reiko Shimp, no. 50., February 8, 1945; (4pp.) (Box 44, Folder 10)
    - A confidential report by Major John C. Hazlett, the new commanding officer who succeeded Colonel Austin at Tule Lake, to a higher command., February 13, 1945; (1p.) (Box 44, Folder 10)
      re A raid on the headquarters of the Seinendan organizations in the Tule Lake Center by the WRA Internal Security Police and representatives of the Justice Department.
    - A clipping from the San Francisco Examiner., February 14, 1945; (1 item) (Box 44, Folder 10)
      re Transfer of Colonel Austin to a new command post at Papago Park, Arizona.
    - A clipping from the Klamath Falls Herald News., February 14, 1945; (1 item. (Box 44, Folder 10)
      re Raid on the headquarters of the Seinendan organizations in Tule Lake.
    - The Newell Star, vol. II, no. 7., February 15, 1945; (6pp.) (Box 44, Folder 10)
    - Tsuru Reiko Shimp, no. 51., February 15, 1945; (4pp.) (Box 44, Folder 10)
    - The Newell Star, vol. II, no. 8., February 22, 1945; (5pp.) (Box 44, Folder 10)
    - Tsuru Reiko Shimp, no. 52., February 22, 1945; (4pp.) (Box 44, Folder 10)
    - The Newell Star, vol. II, no. 9., March 2, 1945; (6pp.) (Box 44, Folder 10)
    - Tsuru Reiko Shimp, no. 53., March 2, 1945; (4pp.) (Box 44, Folder 10)
  - Austin's handwritten chronologies of events before the November 1944 incident in the Tule Lake Center., September 16-November 5, 1943; (Manuscript, 42pp.) (Box 44, Folder 11)
  - An English translation of a patriotic leaflet circulated in the Tule Lake Center., n.d.; (1 item) (Box 44, Folder 12)
  - Battalion Intelligence Officer's copies of censored correspondence exchanged between the Army stockade internees and their families and friends., December 18, 1943-May 26, 1944; (299 letters) (Box 44, Folder 13-14)
  - Pick-up lists of troublemakers for confinement in the Army stockade., ca. November 6, 1943-April 13, 1944; (17 items) (Box 44, Folder 15)
  - Informants' letters on troublemakers., December 1943-May 1944; (11 pieces) (Box 44, Folder 16)
  - Documents and records re the release of the stockade internees., December 1943-August 1944; (11 items) (Box 44, Folder 17)
  - Individual petitions and the Coordinating Committee recommendations submitted for the release of the stockade internees., November 30, 1943-March 1, 1944; (9 items) (Box 44, Folder 18)
  - Copies of the approved orders issued by W.E. Schmidt, Chief of the Administrative Police, WRA, for the release of individual stockade internees., February 22-May 11, 1944; (100 pieces) (Box 44, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous papers re the Tule Lake Center., December 1943-May 1944; (4 items) (Box 44, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous documents and records., 1943-1945 (Box 45, Box 248)
    re the Tule Lake Center; Austin's personal correspondence; and materials on 752nd Military Police Battalion.
    - Copies of the clinical records on the stockade internees who participated in the hunger strike in January 1944., January 1-8, 1944; (145 items) (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - Front pages of the San Francisco Examiner, reporting the Tule Lake incident., November 3-16, 1943; (14 items) (Box 45, Folder 2)
    - Clippings of newspaper articles on the Tule Lake Center and its incident., August 18, 1943-April 11, 1944 and 1954-1967; (92 items) (Box 45, Folder 3)
    - Photographs of the stockade internees, Okamoto's funeral and others., ca. 1944-1945; (8 pieces) (Box 45, Folder 4)
    - War Relocation Authority, Tule Lake Segregation Center., n.d.; (ii + 20pp. Mimeographed, 1 item) (Box 45, Folder 5)
      Information concerning Tule Lake Center, Newell, California. An information pamphlet printed by WRA.
    - Personal correspondence of Verne Austin., January 1944-September 1962; (20 letters) (Box 45, Folder 6)
      re the Tule Lake Center.
    - A History of the 752nd Military Police Battalion., (1 item: Manuscript, typewritten, 11pp.) (Box 45, Folder 7)
      A chronology.
    - Papers re the Army evaluation reports on officers., 1946-1947; (5 items) (Box 45, Folder 8)
    - Photographs of the Tule Lake Center and Army officers under his command at Tule Lake., ca. 1943-1945; (38 pieces) (Box 45, Folder 9)
    - Issei, Nisei, Kibei: The U.S. has put 110,000 people of Japanese blood in 'protective custody'. Fortune., April 1944; (9pp. 1 item) (Box 45, Folder 10)
    - The Denson Tribune, vol. II, no. 32 (April 21, 1944); and the Denson Jiho [characters], no. 144 (April 21, 1944)., (2 items) (Box 45, Folder 11)
      Semi-weekly newspaper published in the Jerome Relocation Center, Denson, Arkansas.
    - Miscellaneous papers collected by Austin on subversive organizations, civilian components in the Army and other topics., 1943-1948; (6 items) (Box 45, Folder 12)
    - The Battle of Tule Lake: Setting the rising sons. A melee with an aftermath -- compiled from the press of the nation and from personal correspondence., 1943-1944; (1 oversize scrapbook) (Box 248)
      Contains newspaper clippings and personal correspondence re the Tule Lake Incident.
    - Photographs and mementos of the 752nd Military Police Battalion., 1943-1945; (1 oversize scrapbook) (Box 248)
      Includes The Tulelake Guardsman, vol. I, nos. 1-11 (December 1943-December 1944) and vol. II, nos. 1-2 & 10 (January-February & October 1945).